hey guys I think this is such a cool
problem we have this blue circle
centered at the origin and we have this
red line that's tangent to the circle
with the equation 4x + 3 y = 12 and they
want us to solve for the radius of the
blue circle I really like the solution
to this one if you want to try this on
your own pause it right now cuz I'm
going to solve it in 3 2 1 first
important detail is a radius and a
tangent line will always meet at right
angles so let's make this a right angle
next I want to find the X and Y
intercepts we probably could just
eyeball them and see that the Y
intercept is 4 and the x intercept is 3
but if for some reason we don't trust
the graph we can find the intercepts
from this equation we know on the Y
intercept the X will equal Z and we know
in the x intercept the Y will equal zero
so we can make an XY table where for the
Y intercept we'll plug in zero for x and
for the x intercept we'll plug in 0 for
y so let's do that we'll copy down this
4x + 3 y = 12 we'll plug in 0 for the X
and 4 * 0 is zero so all this will
vanish and then we have 3 y = 12 and
after we divide both sides by 3 we get y
is equal to 4 and that is going to be
our Y intercept and we can update that
up here and we can do the same thing for
the x intercept we'll plug in zero for
the Y which will make all this disappear
and then after we divide both sides by
four we get X is equal to 3 and that's
going to be the x intercept and we can
change that right here so now that we've
verified our intercepts let's draw this
right triangle this side is going to be
the distance from 0 0 to 04 which is
four and this side will be the distance
of three and since it's a right triangle
it's a Pythagorean triple it's going to
be a 3 45 right triangle so now let's
focus on this triangle and make a
duplicate and then rotate it and move it
down here so these two triangles are the
exact same triangle one is just rotated
so the area of the top one should be
equal to the area of the bottom one well
for the top one the area is2 * the base
of three time the height of four and for
the bottom one the area is 1/2 * the
base of 5 * the height of R and now we
can simplify this on the left hand side
3 * 4 is 12 and 1 12 of 12 is 6 and on
the right hand side 12 * 5 is 5 in order
to get the r by itself I'm going to
multiply both sides of the equation by
the reciprocal of 5ves which is 2 fths
on the left hand side the six gets
multiplied by the two to give us 12 fths
and on the right hand side these cancel
each other out so we have R is equal to
12 fths and we can give it a label of
units and put a box around it so in this
situation the radius is 12 fths units
how exciting wasn't that a neat solution
setting the two triangles equal to each
other